[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Welcome to software engineering radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Luca Palmary. Luca Palmiri is
the author of zero to production in Rust
and focuses on back-end development
software architecture and the Rust
programming language. He works at main
matter as a principal engineer
consultant. He was formerly at AWS True
Layer and has been part of the Rust
community since 2018, which is a long
time. When he's not coding, you'll find
him baking cakes or rolling pasta
sheets. Nice. Luka, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio. Is there anything I
missed in your bio that you'd like to
add? I would say that's pretty accurate
and first and foremost, thanks for
having me. I think probably the only
thing that's miss is I'm an open- source
software developer as well. So I
maintain a variety of projects on top of
my employment duties. Let's call it that
way. And is that quite rust heavy or
just a good mixture primarily Rust I
would say at this stage at least the
ones I'm actively working on. Excellent.
And when was the last time you made
pasta sheets? That must have been a
couple of weeks ago. So not that long
ago. Oh, that's cool. Yeah, I got you on
the show because I really enjoyed
reading your book which we've mentioned
in the intro zero to production in Rust.
It helped me understand some sort of
specific Rust development practices in
relation to the back end. So I'd like to
talk about that if it's okay with you.
Yeah, more than happy to. So to begin
with, I'd like to have an overview in
your own words of what production Rust
code is. So I would say that in one way
it's not very different from production
code in any other language. There are
some specific operational challenges
that one must prepare for whenever he
deploys any kind of software in a
production environment. You need to know
when it fails. You need to be able to
restore it to a good state. You need to
be able to keep an eye on warnings and
understand what's going on without
necessarily being able to print line
debug or try to do things that mess up
with the state of the software. Then the
Rust aspect of it is how to accomplish
those non-functional goals if you want
using the tools that the Rust ecosystem
provides and the Rust programming
language provides. So it's how to
decline all these solutions and all
these challenges in the specific context
of Rust. That's the kind of gap the
niche that the book tries to fill.
Perfect. And can any Rust code be put
into production or is there a certain
technique you have to do when you create
it or compile it, build it? Generally
speaking, deploying RAS code is fairly
easy in so far as Ras binaries tend to
be self-contained plus minus the
occasional system library dependency if
you're linking into some C libraries
like compressions or some TLS libraries.
So bringing Rust into production can
usually be done either by shipping the
row binary which you can compile for the
architecture you're supposed to deploy
to or by shipping a very minimal Docker
container that contains the Ras binary
which is pretty nice because it makes
Rust production deployments fairly
lightweight. The images are small. You
don't have to ship at runtime as you
would do if you were shipping a docker
image of JavaScript or Python or of C
for example. So that makes them quite
nice also in environments like
serverless when the size of what you're
trying to deploy matters for cold starts
and similar concerns. But yeah,
generally speaking is you need to
compile your code into an artifact. The
process is fairly straightforward and
then you push that artifact in whatever
way the platform of choice you picked
likes to be ended artifacts. That could
be in a Docker container, that could be
in a zip file, that could be an FTP if
we are doing something the old fashioned
way. Is there a specific Docker image
that you recommend that people should
use because it's based on a base image
type thing, isn't it? Yes and no. So,
when you build Rust Docker images,
you're usually doing what's called a
multi-stage Docker build. So, you'll
have a first stage where you are
compiling your artifact. In that stage,
you'll need the tool chain. So, you'll
need Ras compiler, you'll need cargo,
potentially additional tooling depending
on the specifics of your project. But
after that stage, the only thing you
care about is the binary that's being
compiled. So you would normally then
copy that from the first stage to a
second stage. And the second stage
wouldn't have anything that is RA
specific. It would only be a base image,
which depending on your constraints
might be something like a Debian slim
base image. Could also be a distless
base image. And if you are particularly
concerned about the size of the image,
you would even push it on a scratch
image. So really you don't need much
beyond the operating system and whatever
as I said before system dependencies you
may have. So if you depend on OpenSSL,
you need to make sure that OpenSSL is in
your runtime layer. But other than that
really like you're free to pick whatever
operating system you prefer. There's a
concept of profiles, isn't there in
Rust? Yes. What would you pick for
production code? So production usually
you would pick so for those who haven't
used Ras before there's two default
profiles dev or debug and release. Debug
is optimized for fast compilation at the
cost of runtime performance. So programs
programmed in debug will generally be a
loss lower than programs programmed in
release. Release takes longer to compile
but squeezes out more performance in the
final artifact and usually the artifact
is also smaller. So generally speaking
you would go off with the release
profile. You can further customize it.
There are things that you can enable and
disable depending on what you're trying
to achieve. You could, for example,
choose to include the bug symbols in
your final artifact. If you want to do
something like collect stack traces in
production, you could choose to minimize
the size of the binary, perhaps
exchanging it for some performance
penalty. You could choose to do link
time optimization of various kinds,
which could result in higher runtime
performance. You could do something like
profile guided optimization if you have
collected traces of your application
running and you know which parts are hot
and which parts are cold. So the
baseline is that release will be good
enough and then from there you can do a
bit of release engineering to try to
tailor the profile to your specific
needs but that's generally something
that doesn't matter for first
deployment. Could you just take me
through those last two again? I didn't
quite understand. I hadn't heard them
before. Link time optimization is
something that relates to the way
compilers usually link together multiple
libraries into one final artifact. So if
you are looking at Rust where you
compile your Rust application, this Rust
application will usually have a
dependency tree. The dependency tree
will be composed of libraries that might
be your libraries or third party
libraries which can number in the tens
in the hundreds and the thousands
depending on how complex the project is.
The rest compiler compiles each of those
dependencies on their own. We say that
the crate is the compilation unit. So
every library is compiled into an
intermediate artifact and then those are
linked into one at the end. This may
cause the compiler to miss some
optimization opportunities. A common
optimization that compilers try to
perform is in lining. So if your
function calls another function but the
function is very short perhaps the
compiler might remove the interaction
and just inline the body of the second
function directly into the body of the
calling function. Trying to do these
optimizations across the create boundary
can be difficult. And this is a
trade-off between compilation
performance and the performance of the
final artifact. By splitting the
compilation into smaller units
independent units the compiler can
compile different units in parallel. So
it allows you your final artifact to be
built faster, but by splitting them up,
it may miss these chances to try to
squeeze a little bit more performance.
So Rust has two options really. One is
the compilation units and the other one
is the link time optimization which you
can configure to try to recover these
optimizations at the cost of
significantly longer compile times. And
the create is a rust library, isn't it?
Yes, the crate is a rust library. The
other I was talking about is
profileguided optimization. By the way,
none of these things are specific to
REST in general. You'll find similar
concepts also in C++ or generally
anything that is compiled. So profile
guided optimization refers to using
runtime information to optimize the
final artifact. So when the RS compiler
looks at your application, it doesn't
know that 99.9% of the times, for
example, where folks try to hit one of
your authenticated endpoints, the
authentication will be successful. So it
doesn't necessarily know that the error
path will be invoked rarely. So it
assumes that all branches with some
caveats are equally likely and so
compiles the program without making any
specific assumptions. What you can do is
you can collect some runtime information
the specific formats for doing this.
Also not an expert necessarily in the
technique but you can collect this
runtime information and then when you
compile your artifact you tell the
compiler look this is what this program
usually does at runtime. And so the
compiler can then use the runtime
information to say well let me make it
so that the stuff that's commonly used
is as optimized as possible perhaps
penalizing a little bit some other code
parts. This is something for example
that the Ras compiler does to optimize
itself. So when you download a binary of
the Ras compiler on Linux that is
profileguided optimized. So they have
collected runtime traces of compiling
RAS programs and then used those to
optimize the compilation of the Ras
compiler itself squeezing out a few
percentage points of performance if I
recall correctly. So it's a technique
that if you are really trying to get the
fastest binary possible is something
that should be in your portfolio of
optimizations. Yeah, that's something
I've not come across. I've done quite a
bit of C as well, profileguided
optimizations and that's not specific to
Rust. No, I mean it comes from LLVM, the
the underlying machinery that Rust uses
to generate native code. So, anything
that uses LLVM, I suppose, should be
able to leverage BJL. I'll put something
in the show notes with a link to that
page on the LLVM website. Excellent. So
are there any specific features of Rust
that we need to consider when building a
production grade application that we've
missed? Features in particular? I
wouldn't say so. There's patterns that
you need to be aware of which we may
touch later on like the way you handle
errors, the way you handle logging those
errors, the way you handle panics for
example. But generally speaking, I would
say there's no specific language feature
that you need to be mindful of. Perfect.
Okay, I'm going to move us on to our
next section which is to explore a
complete app and then go through a few
bits in your book that I that were new
to me and I really enjoyed. So in your
book you take us through a complete
application from development to
production and it's really enjoyable to
see that workflow and understand the
different bits of it cuz usually you
just see this is how you do the rust bit
or this is how you do that bit and so
it's nice to see a whole A to Z of that
workflow. So what does the app do in
your book? So it's a very very simple
newsletter management application which
you can use to send newsletters out to
subscribers. It's complex enough that we
need to care about authentication,
database management, little bit of front
end like the bare minimum, but simple
enough as you say that in roughly 600
pages, we can go from absolutely no code
to a reasonably complete application
that fulfills the spec that we set out
to build. So, we are able to send emails
out. We're able to add subscribers.
We're able to verify their emails. We're
able to verify that the person who's
sending the newsletter in is actually an
admin. All those little key
functionality that you almost always
find in any production application. And
it's sort of API based, isn't it? Web
API. Yeah. Mostly we focus on the back
end because the front end especially
when the book was first written so a few
years ago there wasn't really much about
Rust on the front end beyond using Rust
as web assembly modules. Now there are a
bit more Ras front end frameworks at
this point in time but still my
recommendation would be to stick to more
consolidated choices unless you have a
very compelling reason to try to push
Rust into the browser. Yeah, it
shouldn't really matter what's in the
back end if it's just API based. Just
pick whatever framework you want. Yes.
So in your book you talk about an inner
development loop. Could you take us
through what you mean by that? So the
inner development loop is the cycle of
actions that you perform on your local
machine to validate what you're doing.
So in a language like Rust, this might
be I have my editor open. I am trying to
implement a little feature or a little
piece of functionality. So I'll write a
bunch of code and then I want to check
if it compiles and I want to check if
I've written any tests, if it passes the
tests. And I want to be able to do this
as fast as possible because the faster I
can get feedback, the faster I can
iterate on any mistakes or move on to
the next task. And this is really a
concept that ports to any language. In
other languages, they may not be
compiled. So for example, if you're
working with Python, this would be
trying to execute the tests and perhaps
do some explorative debugging or
explorative usage of the application to
make sure that it works. Now since Rust
is compiled, that makes it so that
generally this inner development loop is
going to be slower than a dynamically
typed language because you have that
compilation step. So what you want to
try to do is you want to try to organize
your project in such a way that we try
to minimize this penalty. So we try to
make the compilation as fast as
possible. We try to break down our
project in smaller units so that they
compile faster independently and we try
to keep our test suits faster. Generally
that is the goal to maximize the number
of iterations that we can do per unit of
time. And you touched upon the structure
of your Rust project there. I can't
remember if it was your book or
somewhere else. I'd read some tips on
having lots of different files and
working on the one file because that's
the only one that will change. So the
Rust compiler won't build everything
again if it was all in in one file as it
were. Did I understand? Unfortunately,
that is not true. That goes back to what
we were discussing before around the way
Rust compiles a project. So the unit
compilation is the library is the crate.
So if you change one file inside one
crate, the Ras compiler will still have
to recompile the whole crate. Now this
is not a complete recompilation. So the
rest compiler supports incremental
compilation where it'll save a bunch of
information from the previous
compilation attempt to try to speed up
the next compilation attempt. So we'll
try to cache as much as possible but
generally speaking you work on the crate
as a compilation unit. So if you want to
speed up compilation for your project
what you want to do is you want to break
it down into crates. It doesn't matter
too much if the files are big or small
because the files are not a unit. So if
you have a large project, you may want
to build you may want to split it out
into vertical slices. For example, if
you're doing domain driven design, you
may want to split it out in the
different domains that compose your
application. And then that domain
functionality will span from the API
layer to the domain logic all the way to
your integration with the database. You
may also choose to slice it
horizontally. So you may have an API
crate, a domain crate, and a DB crate.
Or you could do both things at the same
time. So you can slice it into user
flows and then each flow can be sliced
down horizontally into the specific
subcomponents. What's important is that
you don't end up with a single crate
with tens or hundreds of thousands of
lines of code cuz then your inner
development loop would really take a hit
in terms of speed. Yeah, I think it was
the Z Rust editor or IDE. It's not
specific to Rust, but I was reading the
source code there and it had everything
in different crates and used Rust
workspaces. Is that the sort of pattern
that you mean? Exactly. And you can see
this in every sufficiently large open
source R project. So Zad is an example
of that. UV the Python package manager.
If you open the UV GitHub repository,
you'll see something along the lines
probably 20 30 crates. If you open the
Ras compiler itself, you'll see that
it's split up into a lot of crates.
Probably in the 30s, if not more. I
haven't checked it out in a while. Uh
yes, like you want to try to make those
units as smaller as possible without
going too granular. This is very
important. Like there are consequences
to splitting things out into separate
libraries. You can't access items from
other libraries with the same freedom of
the same level of access that you can
access things in the same library if
they live in different files. So you
need to find the right boundaries
otherwise that's going to be a bit
cumbersome to work with. I'll get some
show notes off you and put those links
to the Python codebase and that other
one you just mentioned. Do you recommend
that they would be individual separate
libraries that would be crates on
crates.io where you download packages or
would they be a workspace within the
same project or is that the same thing?
It's orthogonal in so far as if you're
developing an application that's
proprietary that you need to deploy
yourself as a binary somewhere. You
don't need to publish your sub libraries
anywhere. More often than not, those
wouldn't be open source. So you wouldn't
publish them because you don't want the
source code to be divulged. So you don't
need to care about the registry. The
registry is only something you care
about if you need to distribute whatever
you're building as a library or a binary
for other people to use and you want
that to be open source. For example, I
maintain a Ras framework called Pavx
which contains a binary called Pavx and
Pav C. And these binaries are CLIs that
you need to use to perform some tasks.
Those binaries to try to make them
compile fast. I have broken them down
into smaller libraries. Since I want to
publish the binary to the registry, I am
forced to also publish the sub libraries
to the registry because the constraint
is nothing can be on creat.io the rest
package registry unless all its
dependencies are. So even if those sub
libraries are not really meant to be
used independently they're not
standalone libraries for you to consume.
I still need to publish those to the
registry because I want to publish the
binary. But that's really a concern
specific of open source software. If
you're doing closed source development
perhaps in a company which has three,
four, five, six teams, you might have an
internal registry which is private and
you would publish there the libraries
that different teams need to use across
different applications unless you're
using a monor repo. So you might want to
publish there your telemetry library.
You might want to publish there some
company specific implementation of I
don't know o or some data store specific
bits and then that needs to be reused
across multiple projects. It helps if it
goes into a registry either public or
private depending on your constraints.
Thanks. And do they always have to be in
your workspace within the Rust project
or is that something you decide upon if
you want to share versions and
dependencies? Cuz that's what it means,
isn't it? Yes, that depends. As I said,
if you're doing a monorreo, then you
would do a gigantic Rust workspace with
all the Rust things in one place.
Otherwise, if you're doing a more
classic development model where like
different microservices, let's say, have
their own repositories, then they would
be brought into your project as
dependencies from the registry. So, they
wouldn't need to be in your workspace.
You would simply say, give me my company
telemetry and then you would specify
that it comes from the name of the
private registry so that it doesn't try
to pull it from creatio the public
registry. And if we go back to the first
part of this show, the Docker image
doesn't care about this. We're just
doing cargo builds. It knows what to do
based on the TOML file we've got in our
project and it'll go off and find
everything and do what it needs to do.
Correct. Now, if you're using a private
registry, you might have to care about
authentication probably. So your Docker
image will have to have a way to
authenticate with your company specific
registry in such a way that it can pull
down the libraries it needs because
those wouldn't be copied with a copy
statement because they wouldn't be in
the same repository. But these are all
annoying details that you can figure out
and the specifics depend on what
registry you're using and how to
authenticate. But it's all doable. And
earlier you said the debug profile was
faster than the release profile. If we
think about speed at the moment, do you
have any rules of thumb of when to reach
for these multi- crates or workspace
type project setups or it's one of the
first things you hear about Rust or
building Rust is slow? But have we got
any numbers around that in your
experience? It's difficult to have
numbers because it really depends on the
type of code you're writing. Yeah. Well,
let's take your open source project you
were just talking about. Oh, yeah. Can
you remember what it was like before you
split everything up? It's difficult to
make this comparison, right? because
it's not like it was the same lines of
code. Yeah, true. And in general, it's
difficult to like I wouldn't recommend
going and developing a large project in
a single library. Everything is
entangled with everything else. Then
splitting it up is going to be
complicated. Generally speaking, what I
would suggest is the normal good
practice of software development. So
even if something is inside a single
library, try to have clean interfaces
between your modules. At a certain point
when you decide the compilation is too
slow perhaps because a recompilation
from a warm cache takes 30 seconds
that's a long time or 20 seconds that's
still a long time then you can say okay
well these modules that are kept nice
and self-contained now I'll make that a
library you need to keep the modularity
in mind as you are developing the
project because otherwise you need to go
through a painful refactor to first
change the internal structure of your
library to have a clearly isolated
module and then pull that out into
library. It's not very difficult from
trying to break a monolith a monolithic
application. You need to have it
structured in such a way that is
possible. If not, then you need to spend
the time refactoring to make sure that
then it becomes possible. So, we're
going to get a gut feeling really when
things start to get slow because you'll
have been writing that code since the
start. So, you know that it's getting
slower and slower basically. Yes,
exactly. And is there anything in the
container world that would help with a
big build of a rust project in the build
layer as it were or when you're building
docker containers you need to try to
optimize for docker layer caching. So
although we have said up until now about
the inner development flow relies on
incremental compilation. So Rust having
a fairly detailed cache from what it did
during the previous compilation attempt
to try to speed up the current
compilation attempt. when you are
compiling in CI or more generally trying
to build Docker containers, incremental
compilation is not going to be
particularly useful because a Docker
layer is invalidated as soon as anything
from the previous step has changed. So a
technique that you can try to deploy is
to try to cache your dependency tree. So
you don't try to cache the intermediate
artifacts of your libraries, the one
that exists in your repository. you try
to cache all the compilation work that
was done for your dependencies because
those come from the registry and as long
as their versions haven't changed
they'll result in exactly the same
intermediate compilation artifacts. So
you try to structure your docker build
as a multi-stage build as we were saying
at the beginning to try to have a step
where you compile your dependency tree
then a step where you compile your
application and then you copy the final
artifact into the runtime image and as
long as your dependency tree so your
lock file really your cargo.lo block
file hasn't changed, that layer will be
cached. So you'll then you're just
rebuilding your projects, which is
usually going to be a much smaller
percentage of the total build time. And
you should be able to push a Rust image
to production in I don't know a minute
perhaps, something along those lines.
That's the target number I usually try
to strive for mostly because the time it
takes to push something is very closely
related to how long it takes you to
patch an incident. So you want to keep
that small. The specific project I will
look into which I maintain for doing
docker layer caching and is the one used
in the book is called cargo chef cargo
the ras package manager doesn't support
this locker layer friendly layout out of
the box. So you need a third party tool
to make it nice. So the cargo.lock file
and the cargo.l file that you see in a
normal rush project. The dotlock file is
all your dependencies. So that's a trick
you can do to speed up the docker build.
Yeah. So the toml file is the
specification. So it's about I'm happy
for example to get any dependency any sd
version which is 1.0 or above. So you
specify a sember range in your toml
files. The lot file contains the result
of the version resolution algorithm. So
the cargo package manager will look at
all your toml file. We look at all your
versions. We look at the version
requirements of your dependency
recursively until it's built the whole
tree. and then it'll try to figure out a
version for each library that kind of
fits all the requirements and it'll save
that resolution into the LO file. So as
long as you don't explicitly change your
dependency tree either by updating or by
introducing new dependency or by
removing dependencies, your LO file will
stay stable. And so as long as your LO
file stays stable, the exact
dependencies you're pulling in won't
change. This is very similar to LO files
in other languages. I think JavaScript
has a similar concept. Python has
several implementations in this for
different package managers. So it's the
split between what I want and what I
get. And you said you need Cargo Chef to
be able to do that in you need cargo
chef to be able to take a cargo lock as
input and just build the dependencies
without building the local packages.
Cargo build wouldn't do that by cargo
build would build the whole project. So
it will build all your dependencies and
your code. But it's safe to assume that
if you are building a new image is
because your code has changed. So if
you're doing in docker a copy dot dot
which is bring all the files into the
image and then you do a cargo build
what's coming in via that copy has
certainly changed with respect to the
previous time you try to build the
docker image. So that would result in a
docker layer cache miss and so your
cargo build would be building fresh. So
you would always be starting from
scratch which is very it's a really good
hack isn't it as they say. Oh yeah, for
speeding up Rust project builds. Some
would say that it would be nicer if
Cargo supported something of the sort
natively and I do concur. In the
meantime, I put together a solution to
kind of stop the bleeding for my own
commercial projects. Perfect. That was
quite a deep dive there. I wasn't
expecting that. I really enjoyed that.
I've got a few questions left in this
section before we move on. So, we'll
maybe have to be brief on them. Sure. So
what key components do we need to think
about given the fact that our newsletter
app is going to be on the internet with
specifics to Rust? I don't think there
is anything unique about this
application versus another API
application written in a different
language. Would you say? Yeah, I would
say like there's nothing specific to
REST as to what you need to be aware of
when it comes to the exposing something
on the internet. The same core
principles apply. So you need to have
some kind of network topology. So make
sure that you're only exposing the ports
that you're planning to expose. It's
good practice to make sure that all the
ports you're exposing to the internet
are protected by TLS, transport layer
security. So you want to use a platform
or provision certificates that the
browser could verify. And then you want
to make sure that your image contains
the minimal amount of things that it
needs to contain to minimize the
security surface so that if somebody
were to be able to somehow gain remote
code execution on your application, they
wouldn't have too many tools to leverage
and you also want to contain what they
could do. So you also want to lock down
what your docker image is able to
connect to. Those I would say are the
key principles. And then the second is
you want some kind of access control on
all the operations that your application
exposes which are privileged. So if
you're looking at our newsletter
application from the book, you need to
be able to send a newsletter. That means
we need to be able to verify that you
are the owner of the newsletter, which
means we need to log in. Every time
you're trying to implement a login that
you have a cascade list of security
requirements, there's various
vulnerabilities you need to be aware of.
You need to protect around CSRF cross
request source forgery. You need to
protect against many in the middle
attacks and the requirements for TLS.
You need to store password in a safe
way. So all of these things are not RS
specific. And this gets back to what I
was saying at the beginning. We're not
breaking new ground here. It's about how
do I do these things in a Rust
application. And that's a challenge
specific to the fact that Rust is a
small standard library too. So in other
languages I think of go the solutions to
a lot of these challenges can be found
in the go stand library. That is not the
case for RS. RS adopts the philosophy of
having a minimal standard library and
pushing these concerns to the ecosystem
which then poses to you the developer
building an application the challenge of
what do I use from the ecosystem? What
can I trust? Does these building blocks
play nice together? Is this better than
this? And so those are some of the
questions that the book tries to answer
and more than answer trying to give you
the tools to answer those questions
yourself in the future for other types
of tasks that you may need to reach out
for the registry. We did a show episode
383 I did with Neil Madden on securing
your API which I highly recommend that
covers a lot of what you just mentioned
as well. Is there anything specific to
Rust given the fact it's strongly typed?
So if we're taking in say a JSON payload
to act on for the newsletter subscriber
adding them or something and say there's
a problem with taking that JSON in and
converting it to a rust enum or
structure using siri that you mentioned
earlier the serialization and
deserialization library or is that just
something we handle in our error
checking and all that type of stuff.
There's two steps to that. The first one
is we need whatever code is doing the
dialization to not have vulnerabilities
and that's about do I use si is si like
a well audited crate and are we sure
that si and the specific format the
serializer we're using in our case that
would be si json do not cause any
vulnerabilities if the payload is
maliciously crafted the second layer is
we need to handle that decalization
error this is usually quite simple so
far as if something fails to decalize,
you would return a variation of a 400
and then you just craft a good error
message. So it's not like the good thing
about RS and actually the deal of the
language is that you can make safety
modular. So since Ras protects you as a
language from a variety of memory and
safety vulnerabilities, as long as you
stiff, you stick to safe R. So you're
not using the unsafe portions of the
language, the one that let you do some
pointer wrangling and other more manual
memory operations. You already know that
a bunch of issues that you may have like
buffer overflows, out of bounds access
if you're trying to access an index that
is beyond the end of an array and
similar bridge heads problems that
attackers would use to then jump from
there to remote code execution or other
kinds of exploits. you already know that
those are patched. So really you can
focus on the logic of your application
and not have to worry too much about
these things as long as you're you made
sure that the dependencies you're using
haven't introduced those vulnerabilities
by incorrect usage of unsafe rest. So
that's why this goes back to you need to
audit your dependency tree and be very
careful into what you bring into your
source tree. This comes under that
umbrella that's been spoken about quite
a lot over the past few years. The
supply chain isn't it? Supply chain
security. Yes. Yeah. With all the big
things that have happened past couple of
years. And I mean there's two aspects to
supply chain security I would say,
right? One aspect is are the people I'm
trusting trustworthy. So do I fear that
at a certain point one of my
dependencies might turn rogue and push
code that is intentionally malicious?
And so this is one part. The other part
is is there a bug that is you know
undetected. It's not maliciously been
planting there but it's in my code. It's
running and exposes my application to
vulnerabilities. Those are two different
type of concerns. There's always a bug,
isn't there? The problem is, is it a
security vulnerability bug or not? And
you know that is a concern that varies
depending on the type of library we're
talking about. The library does
serialization dialization. I mean,
that's a it's a prime target like that's
going to everything that touches
untrusted user input needs to go under
extreme scrutiny. That's not the case
for everything else that's inside your
code. But yeah, anything that's on the
network boundary, the implementation of
transport security, the way you parse
HTTP requests, the way you parse the
bodies, all these things, those need to
be hardened and they need to be battle
tested. Thanks. So, I've got a few
questions left in this section. Like I
said, one of them was where does our
application live? I think we've touched
upon that by explaining that we're going
to put it in a docker and pop it on the
cloud somewhere. How do we get it there
is also covered by that? whether it goes
through our CI pipeline or well we push
an image somewhere and then the platform
makes it so that it goes to the right
place in the book we use digital ocean
because it's simple and convenient but
the specifics will vary depending on if
you're deploying to WS if you're
deploying to Azure if you're using
Terraform so the options are endless as
long as you build image the rest is
language agnostic I would say I was
going to ask how does this compare to
other languages but it's the same it's
yeah it's the same it's the image so the
last one in the section Before we
change, do you have any performance
metrics that would be normal for a
backend Rust application like this one?
As in, let's say we built it in another
language, the exact same thing in the
exact same digital ocean with the exact
same Docker build setup. Can we just
love the fact that Rust is going to be
so much faster or is that still
something we need to think about as a
software engineer? So as long as you use
the same architecture so we are roughly
you know as you said implementing the
same application in the same way in
different languages and we're comparing
let's say Ras to Golang Python node to
use or Java to use some commonly
deployed backend applications as a
reference. We generally would expect the
Rust application to outperform them but
let's be specific as to what that means.
One point we touched before. So your
Docker image is likely going to be
smaller, probably going to be comparable
to Golang, but generally speaking,
you're deploying a Docker image that
it's as small as it could possibly be,
which means that it'll be faster to roll
it out. It'll be faster to scale your
software up and down because whatever is
running the Docker image will take less
time to pull it. After that, there's
three main performance metrics that we
look at. One is how many requests per
second can we handle on a given
hardware? How much memory are we using
and what's the variability in our
latency? So what's the difference
between in jargon is what's the
difference between our 50th percentile
in latency and our 99th percentile in
latency. So let's start from request per
second. In my experience, generally
speaking, if you're building an API,
you're sooner ran into your database not
being able to keep up than your RA code
not being able to keep up because the
Ras code is going to be fairly
efficient. Most of the time it's going
to spend doing IO. RAS is a very
efficient asyn model which allows you to
multiplex multiple tasks concurrently
over the same CPU core. So, you're not
going to be bottlenecked on CPU work. So
it really is about optimizing access to
the data store and in this it's not
particularly unique. Same problems you
will have with different languages which
are reasonably efficient. The difference
is going to be in memory usage. Rust is
fairly parsimonious when it comes to
memory usage and most importantly tends
to clean after itself. So every time
some value is allocated when it goes out
of scope it will be immediately
deallocated and that's because the rest
compiler knows where things are live in
terms of values. This makes it so that
usually Rust applications have a very
small memory footprint. So if the Rust
application isn't doing any work, it's
going to hover around, I don't know,
usually the number I see is around 40 50
60 megabytes of memory usage, it'll go
up proportionally to the amount of
traffic that's coming in and then once
the traffic goes out, that go back down.
So it's fairly easy to do resource
planning because it's very proportional
to the work that's being done. That's a
really big advantage, isn't it? always a
massive advantage especially
operationally like you can look at the
graph like the key system metrics of a
rest application so how much memory am I
using how much CPU am I using what's my
P50 and P99 and you'll see that
generally like they move together with
respect to the number of requests this
is assuming they were talking about
requests do the same thing or roughly
the same amount of work so that makes it
easy to plan how much headroom you need
makes it easy to understand when the
application is to scale so if you need
to configure an autoscaler. It's easier
to know what thresholds to set. It also
makes it easier to understand if
something is wrong. Like if you look at
your RP50, your P99 and the time spent
inside the Rust application. So let's
exclude the variance that comes for
example from the data store. Usually
they'll be pretty flat like the band
will be pretty tight. So if you suddenly
see spikes, that's a sign that something
is wrong. Now generally speaking, all of
these are generalizations. They depend
on the specifics of your application.
But they have deployed Rust applications
quite extensively. Previous workplaces
layer as an example used to have a
variety of languages in production a lot
of C and we have seen that the footprint
of Rust in production is significantly
smaller to the point that our compute
bill was a fraction of the compute bill
for the C# applications handling more or
less the same traffic because we were
part of the same microser architecture.
So generally like you'll get efficiency
out of rest. caveat keep an eye your
data store sooner or later that will be
the bottleneck. Seems to me that Rust is
a very sort of green energy efficient
language as well. Yeah, I mean if we
consider the amount of processing power
being used then Rust will lower that
which in turn will lower the energy
consumption of your applications. So
anything that improves efficiency is
going to result in a cleaner system. Did
we cover the three metrics that you were
going to talk about there? Yeah, I would
say so. So latency, CPU, and uh memory
usage. Yeah, the P50%. Yeah, P50 and
P99. So for those who haven't heard of
this before, it's half of your user will
see a latency that's below the P50. And
99% of your users will see a latency
that is below the P99. The closer the
P99, the P50 are together, the more you
can reason about the average experience
that somebody's having using your API.
And so it's ideal for a system to have
very close bands. So to have a P50
that's very close to their P99 because
that makes it uniformly reliable for
people to use makes the experience very
consistent. And so since RAS has that
very predictable pattern of memory
allocations and the allocations that
usually makes it so that doing the same
amount of work takes the same amount of
time unless the application is under too
much load. And that will make it so that
yeah, your P9 will be reasonably close
to your P50 and this will make it easier
to scale your software. The important
aspect here is that Ras doesn't have a
garbage collector. I'm surprised I
haven't mentioned that so far. So since
RAS doesn't have a garbage collector,
there's not going to be sudden spikes in
your P99. Like you're not going to find
out that mostly it is consistent, but
from time to time we're going to stop
the world in quotes and collect a bunch
of garbage. And so our application will
be busy doing that. So it won't be
serving requests that are coming in and
those requests will be slower. There is
a problem you'll see in C#, a problem
you see in Go. It's been multiple outs.
I think one of the most famous ones is
the one from Discord moving some
services from Go to Rest precisely
because of this reason. So the lack of a
garbage collection feeds into that
predictability. We're going to talk
about telemetry. Let's assume everyone
knows what telemetry is. That's I'll
have a go. sending stuff from your app
to somewhere else so you can see what's
going on. Is that Yep, that's a
reasonable. What options do we have in
the Rust ecosystem for this? So, Rust
has a fairly established library for
collecting telemetry data. It's called
tracing and it works similarly to how
you may have used logging in other
languages. I think of Python as a
reference example. There's an interface
call it a facade. So it gives you a
bunch of methods to record data like log
at the info level, log at the warn
level, log at the error level and then
you can configure your application to
process that telem data in different
ways. So you can install different
subscribers and they will process this
data and ship it off to the terminal or
data dog or oncom or whatever you use
for then querying, searching, sifting
through this telemetry data. The good
thing about Rust once again is that
since the language is compiled and the
it's used in like a wide range of
applications. So from embedded to the
cloud to the browser, the tracing
library is optimized for minimal
overhead which makes it so that whenever
some for example log lines have been
disabled runtime or compile time the
cost of those is going to be minimal. So
you can be pretty liberal in
instrumenting your application and then
it's about setting the right log level
and you can raise it as necessary if you
need to get more telemetry data. The
rest is language agnostic. The golden
metric like the golden goal that you
want to achieve is that you should be
able to troubleshoot your application
based on the telemetry data you are
collecting. If something happens in
production, it's a bug. you know it's a
bug and you look at the logs and you
have no idea what that is about and you
need to deploy new logs that's game over
like you failed. So the idea is we need
to make it so that all the logs are
there that we're capturing the key
information and then then we can raise
the log level as necessary. In the book
we do it with the open telemetry
standard. No we do it with JSON logging.
Usually in production application I
would do it with open telemetry which R
supports and that would allow you also
to kind of link all this instrumentation
across network hops if you have a
microser architecture. But as you said
like it's not really important where the
logs go. The important thing is that
they contain in the first place the
information that we care about. And you
talk about I think you briefly mentioned
it just then the fade pattern. Is that
how you say that? Yeah the facade
pattern. Facade. Yeah of course that's
how you say that word. Sorry. French I
guess. Yeah. Facade pattern means I'm
going to give you an API that's going to
be the same and then underneath that API
you can plug different backends. That's
the most commonly deployed way of doing
logging across most languages. The login
module in Python as I was mentioning
before does the same thing. So you
always use the same functions and then
at the beginning of your application
when you are initializing all the things
you also initialize the login back end
and R does uses the same pattern. So our
takeaways from any type of telemetry in
Rust is that we reach for the tracing
crate or library and that it's really
optimized for browser back end front end
cuz it's heavily used and it doesn't
have any runtime or compile time
downside if we disable a logging or
enable. It has minimal runtime over it
cannot go to zero but it goes as close
to zero as as possible. So there's
nothing we need to be unconfident about
putting that in production.
No, nothing you need to be concerned
about. Obviously, the log lines that are
going to be logged, they're going to
have a cost. So, if you are sending log
lines in the several megabytes ballpark
of size, exporting those is going to be
expensive. So, you need to keep in mind
what data is being pushed and being
pushed where. But other than that, you
can be pretty liberal with having like
trace level debug level log statements
which are a bit more expensive which are
disabled usually but you can enable on
the fly if you need to debug further and
does the tracing create give us what you
call what is commonly known as
structured logging or is that something
different and what it's exactly that
it's exactly that. Okay. So you get log
messages each log so you get you have a
span so by default when you're capturing
something you can capture it duration.
So you can capture when it begins and
where it ends. It has a level so that
you can do filtering based on the level.
It has a location so it tells you where
that span is coming from. So you can say
give me info level logs from my
application crate but give me only one
word level logs from the HTTP dependency
that they use to parse dependencies and
the spawn is important because of
multi-threaded. The spans are important
multi-threaded is more you need to be
careful with that to make sure the spans
are correct but spans are important
because they give you a logical stack
trace. So you can understand if
something happened inside a certain span
or outside and they give you the
duration of an operation which is often
a very important information when
troubleshooting. And the other thing is
that you can capture fields. So name
fields key value pairs which if you then
export to something that has support for
searching them allows you to do
structure queries against that data.
That's good to know Rust is a first
class citizen with open telemetry as
well tracing crate isn't it? Yes. Okay.
So last section, error handling in our
app. What errors could we get? All
sorts. So we could, as we mentioned
before, fail to dialize the payload
that's coming from the user with the
request. We could fail to talk to the
database. The database may not be there.
The database may return an error when we
query it. The database may return data
as a shape that is not what we expected.
We may be failing to talk to our email
provider to send a verification email.
So things can go wrong like that. That's
endless list of things that go wrong.
Now the cool thing about Rust is the way
you model that behavior. So in most
languages that I I've personally used
and I would say most languages that are
currently used in the industry, errors
are modeled as exceptions. So that's the
case for Java, it's the case for C#,
it's the case for Python, etc., etc.
Exception go through an exceptional
control flow if you want. So when you
are programming, you don't really see
exceptions. they jump through the
different uh function calls in your
stack trace and you need to be explicit
about trying to catch them. It's a very
non-local type of error handling. So
something very deep in your call stack
may raise an exception that you're
handling 6 7 15 layers up. The problem
with exceptions is this non- locality
when you need to recover from the error.
So as long as you know if as long as you
don't care you let it bubble up to the
top return a 500 and log it. That's the
easy part. The complicated part is where
you need to do different things
depending on what error has occurred.
And so you then need to say, okay, I
need to catch it. I need to catch it
with the right type of exception. And
that may happen in a different place.
And so when you change the location
where the error is emitted, perhaps the
error type changes, but you forget to
change your try catch somewhere else.
And then suddenly your rendering flow is
broken. If you have a test, you may
catch it. If you don't have a test,
that's a bug that goes straight to
production. Rust like many functional
programming languages like Okamel, Ascal
and the likes instead models errors as
values. So you have a type called
result. It's a Rust enim. So it has two
variants. The okay variant returns the
data in the case the operation was
successful. The error variant returns an
error in case the operation was
unsuccessful. The error is typed just
like the okay variant. So you can have
different error types that contain
different error information. And you
can't access this access value unless
you specify what to do in the error
path. So you're always forced to handle
the error case if there is an error
case. Handling the error case usually
means using a match statement. So
specifying two code paths, one for the
epic case and one for the error case. In
most situations, you'll want to bubble
up the error. So you want to return an
error from the function that kind of
contains the other error as a source.
Other times you may want to log it. You
may want to swallow it. You may want to
do some default logic. But since all of
this is explicit and captured in the
type system, if the error type changes,
if a new failure mode is introduced,
very often your code will fail to
compile. So the rest compiler will tell
you, hey, here you said that you're
handling the case where the record is
not found, but now there's a new error.
There's also the case where the
connection fails to be established. You
need to tell me what to do in that case.
And this makes it so generally speaking,
based also my professional experience,
the software breed in Rust tends to be
more stable when it comes to error paths
because the type checker is doing a lot
of the heavy lifting for you to make
sure that you're not forgetting things
along the way. And that's exactly what
we do in the book when trying to
implement the newsletter. We try to
structure good errors. We try to use
enms to explain what the different error
cases are so that we then can handle it
in a structured way where necessary. And
does Rust um give you an escape hatch if
you just don't want to handle the happy
path and the error path? You would
bubble it up. So you can do that.
There's a little bit of syntax sugar.
It's the question mark operator where
you say this thing can fail question
mark. The question mark means if this
function returns an error itself, then
bubble it up as an error to the caller.
And that usually works automatically as
long as the two error types are
compatible. So the error type you are
bubbling up can be converted to the
error type that the current function
returns and that would go up all the way
usually to a middleware somewhere that's
going to convert it into 500 and log it.
Yeah with specifics to the API that we
want to return to the user. Okay, I'm
going to move us along now. You talk
about an internal error and an edge
error. Is that something specific to
Rust or just to this backend
application? I would say is a general
software development pattern. When you
talk about edge errors, you're talking
about the error conditions that the user
can see. So this is the contract of your
API if you want. If I call this
endpoint, what responses may I get back?
And most API documentation will usually
be very to row in documenting the AP
case but will usually underdocument the
AP case. So the least amount of
responses, but a few more may come up in
practice. So you want to be very careful
in designing those edge errors because
those edge errors need to satisfy
different requirements. So they need to
enable very often some kind of control
flow on the user side. So if I'm calling
an API and I get an error, I need to
determine is this error fatal like if I
retry, may I succeed or will it always
keep failing? So you need to give them
some machine readable information to
make that determination. So we do that
with status codes very often. So you
know that if you get a 400 retrying is
not going to make it succeed. It'll keep
failing because the request is
malformed. If you get a 500 sometimes
that means that you may succeed if you
retry the application can be well
behaved and give you for example retry
after header that explicitly tells you
yeah retry please let's wait a certain
amount of time. We're having a rough
patch will recover. If you get a request
conflict that may succeed if you retry.
So it's about making so that you are
giving structured information to the
caller so that they can build their own
control flow and make it so that they
can automatically recover in the cases
where there is supported or themselves
escalate to an operator uh in the cases
where that's not going to be possible.
So if you get a 400 there's a bug in
implementation like a developer needs to
go and look at it and fix the payload
that's being sent. The other part is
about explaining what is wrong. So if
you give me a 400 it's like okay cool my
request is malformed how like what's
wrong about it? So you also need to have
information that's geared towards the
operator is going to try to handle this
failure to troubleshoot it to fix it. So
you usually want to say well we expected
a field name X the field is not there
and we expected a field name email that
contains a string but your field name
email contains a number that's not going
to get it. So that kind of information
needs to be in the body and that's
something Rust can help with because of
its really strong modeling. Exactly. Are
there any rush practices that we would
use in our day-to-day programming life
that we shouldn't use in production with
regards to error handling? A more
drastic escape patch is instead of
bubbling up the error, you can panic. A
panic in Rust is equivalent to crashing
the program with some caveats. You can
catch some panics, but generally
speaking, it's meant to be a
non-reoverable error that's going to
drop the connection and just unwind the
stack. So when you're doing some
prototyping very often just to you know
try to validate an idea faster it's good
to just panic on errors like yeah sure
I'll handle this later don't want to
ship that to production usually you want
to clean it up first and is that unwrap
as well yeah that's exactly what unwrap
does is this may fail if it's an error
panic otherwise give me the case perfect
so this is a bit specific to your career
you might not be able to give me any
detail on in your answer but if you've
seen any rust code in your career that
you just want to change and rip up
immediately before it goes to
production. I've seen a lot of code that
I wanted to change before it went to
production in many different languages.
This is not specific to Rust. I would
say sometimes you need to develop under
time constraints that don't allow you to
to produce the level of craft that
you'll be proud of. I guess that's a
fairly common experience. Are there any
tools in our beautiful wonderful Rust
ecosystem that can help us go through
the codebase and go hold on a minute if
this going into production you're going
to have problems? Yes. So Rust ships
with a default llinter called Clippy and
Clippy tries to catch a lot of
problematic code patterns usually as a
warning that you can choose to then
respect or ignore. It is good practice
or recommended run cryp clippy CI and
make it fail on warnings. That's what I
do. Yeah. In fact, I used the bear from
your book in one of my own projects.
Yes. And then, you know, sometimes you
can ignore the warnings. Sometimes the
warning is not important, but at least
you need to think about it, which is a
good point of reflection. Have you tried
the 2024 edition of Rust yet? Yeah, I've
already migrated a bunch of projects.
Pretty uneventful migration. I would say
a lot of the tooling does it for you, so
it wasn't too much of a lift. I've been
working on the 2021 Rust edition mainly
cuz it's 2025. And when that came out
last month, I switched on in my own
project, which is a a blend of C and
Rust. And so my big work bit is to put
unsafe unsafe keywords everywhere that I
didn't need before. Yes. Tening the
screws a little bit on unsafe blocks.
And that's good. Yeah, it's a bit of bit
of a chore. Okay, so to summarize that,
there's always bad code before it gets
to production, but cargo clippy can help
us clean up a lot of that. And coverage,
I would say test coverage is always a
good thing to keep a handle on. Yeah, I
saw that in your book about test
coverage. Was it the LLVM? You can use
LLVM code. Yes. Yeah, that's what I I
took from your book and put that in my
own project, too. Cuz there's not much
on the internet about Rust code
coverage, what tools to use. It's been
fragmented because it's historically the
approaches were different than the
compiler gain support for emitting LVM
coverage information and now the that's
the fastest way to get coverage. That
was really good. Very happy we did this
show and I hope that helps others
understand like it did with me how we
take a Rust application from our desktop
and get it into the cloud. What to pick
and what not to pick and all the tools
out there to clean things up. Even
though we did a good deep dive on a lot
of topics, was there anything you think
we missed that we should mention before
we finish? I would say this was pretty
comprehensive. I'll make sure to provide
show notes for some of those deep dives
so you can go and read further. But
other than that, I think this was a good
representation. Yeah, I think we should
definitely put a link to your open
source project and just see how you do
it properly.
That'll be the one to read and everyone
to copy. That's a lot of pressure. Nah,
it's open source. It's always out there
in the open. How can people get in touch
or reach out if they would like to speak
to you or tap into your expertise? Most
social media platforms. So, you'll find
me on Blue Sky, Twitter, and the likes.
And that's my website as well, which has
contact informations. Luca, thank you
for coming on the show. It's been a real
pleasure. This is Gavin Henry for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by IE
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.